‭Well,
‮نحن سوف‮،
‭welcome to soteriology.
‮مرحبا بكم في علم الخلاص‮.
‭This course deals with the Holy Spirit
‮تتناول هذه الدورة موضوع الروح القدس
‭and the doctrine of the Holy Spirit,
‮وعقيدة الروح القدس‮.
‭how the Holy Spirit works in the soul.
‮كيف يعمل الروح القدس في النفس‮.
‭Running all the way from His effectual calling,
‮فراراً من دعوته الفعالة ‮،
‭and regeneration,
‮والتجديد ‮،
‭all the way to glorification.
‮وصولا إلى التمجيد‮.
‭So it's a very important subject
‮لذلك فهو موضوع مهم للغاية
‭and I'm glad you're with me.
‮وأنا سعيد لأنك معي‮.
‭We're going to look at it in some detail.
‮سوف ننظر في الأمر بشيء من التفصيل‮.
‭I think you'll enjoy the class.
‮أعتقد أنك ستستمتع بالفصل‮.
‭After all,
‮بعد كل شيء‮،
‭all of our
‮كل منا
‭Christianity,
‮النصرانية‮،
‭all of our personal religion
‮كل ديننا الشخصي
‭is just a sham without the Holy Spirit.
‮مجرد خدعة بدون الروح القدس‮.
‭So we're very,
‮لذلك نحن جدا ‮،
‭very grateful for the ministry of the Holy Spirit,
‮ممتن جدا لخدمة الروح القدس ‮،
‭I want to begin this
‮أريد أن أبدأ هذا
‭first lecture with the reading of God's word,
‮المحاضرة الأولى بقراءة كلمة الله ‮،
‭as we will with each each lecture.
‮كما نفعل مع كل محاضرة‮.
‭Turn with me,
‮استدر معي ‮،
‭please,
‮من فضلك‮،
‭to Romans 8 and I'll read 13 through 17.
‮إلى رومية ٨ وسأقرأ من ٣١ إلى ٧١‮.
‭Romans 8: 13 through 17.
‮رومية ٨: ٣١ حتى ٧١‮.
‭For,
‮إلى عن على‮،
‭if you live after the flesh,
‮إذا كنت تعيش بعد الجسد ‮،
‭you shall die.
‮تموت‮.
‭But if ye
‮ولكن إذا كنتم
‭through the Spirit do mortify,
‮من خلال الروح تميت ‮،
‭the deeds of the body
‮أفعال الجسد
‭ye shall live.
‮ستعيشون‮.
‭For as many as are led
‮لكثير من الذين يقودون
‭by the Spirit of God,
‮بروح الله
‭they are the sons of God.
‮هم ابناء الله‮.
‭For you have not received the Spirit
‮لأنك لم تقبل الروح
‭of bondage again to fear,
‮من العبودية مرة أخرى للخوف ‮،
‭but you have received the Spirit of adoption
‮ولكنك قد قبلت روح التبني
‭whereby we cry Abba,
‮حيث نبكي أبا ‮،
‭Father.
‮أب‮.
‭The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit
‮الروح نفسه يشهد لأرواحنا
‭that we are the children of God,
‮أننا أبناء الله ‮،
‭and if children then heirs,
‮وإذا كان الأبناء ثم الورثة ‮،
‭heirs of God and joint heirs with Christ.
‮ورثة الله ووارثون مشتركون مع المسيح‮.
‭If so be
‮إذا كان الأمر كذلك
‭that we suffer with him,
‮التي نعانيها معه ‮،
‭that we may also be glorified together.
‮حتى نتمجد ايضا معا‮.
‭Let's seek God's face in prayer.
‮دعونا نطلب وجه الله في الصلاة‮.
‭Lord God,
‮ربنا يارب
‭we stand on holy ground,
‮نقف على أرض مقدسة ‮،
‭as we approach this
‮ونحن نقترب من هذا
‭immense subject of the third person of the Holy Trinity
‮موضوع هائل للشخص الثالث من الثالوث الأقدس
‭and his salvific work in our souls.
‮وعمله الخلاصي في نفوسنا‮.
‭And we do pray that
‮ونحن نصلي ذلك
‭by the end of this course,
‮بنهاية هذه الدورة ‮،
‭we will have a much more profound appreciation
‮سيكون لدينا تقدير أكثر عمقا
‭for the saving ministry of the Holy Spirit,
‮لخدمة الروح القدس الخلاصي ‮،
‭than we perhaps might have at present
‮مما قد يكون لدينا في الوقت الحاضر
‭Help us to grow,
‮ساعدنا على النمو ‮،
‭not only in the grace and knowledge of Jesus,
‮ليس فقط بنعمة يسوع ومعرفته ‮،
‭whom the Spirit focuses upon,
‮الذي يركز عليه الروح ‮،
‭but also that we would grow
‮ولكن أيضًا أننا سننمو
‭in the grace and knowledge of the Holy Spirit,
‮بنعمة الروح القدس ومعرفته ‮،
‭becoming more aware of His work,
‮أن يصبح أكثر وعياً بعمله ‮،
‭His saving work,
‮عمله الخلاصي ‮،
‭and appreciating more profoundly
‮وتقدير أكثر عمقا
‭the vastness of His ministry
‮اتساع خدمته
‭as he works in sinners and rebels,
‮كما يعمل في الخطاة والمتمردين ‮،
‭such as we all are by nature.
‮مثلنا جميعًا بطبيعتنا‮.
‭So Lord bless this class.
‮لذلك بارك الرب هذا الفصل‮.
‭Help me in teaching.
‮ساعدني في التدريس‮.
‭Help the students in listening,
‮مساعدة الطلاب في الاستماع ‮،
‭learning,
‮التعلم‮،
‭and grant that each lecture
‮وامنح ان كل محاضرة
‭may serve to thy glory,
‮قد يخدم مجدك ‮،
‭to our spiritual growth,
‮لنمونا الروحي ‮،
‭and to the well-being
‮والرفاهية
‭of our entire being as we journey
‮من كياننا بأكمله أثناء رحلتنا
‭to the never-ending eternity.
‮إلى الأبدية التي لا تنتهي‮.
‭Be with us now we pray.
‮كن معنا الآن نصلي‮.
‭In Jesus name.
‮باسم يسوع‮.
‭Amen.
‮آمين‮.
‭Well,
‮نحن سوف‮،
‭thank you for joining us for this class
‮شكرا لانضمامك إلينا في هذا الفصل
‭and I want to
‮وانا اريد ان
‭begin with the first lecture,
‮تبدأ بالمحاضرة الأولى ‮،
‭which is titled: The Study
‮وهي الدراسة
‭of the Holy Spirit.
‮من الروح القدس‮.
‭The Study of the Holy Spirit.
‮دراسة الروح القدس‮.
‭God's Holy spirit was with God's people from the beginning.
‮كان روح الله القدوس مع شعب الله منذ البداية‮.
‭Already in Genesis 1,
‮بالفعل في تكوين ١ ‮،
‭verse 2
‮الآية ٢
‭leading them ultimately to their rest
‮يقودهم في النهاية إلى راحتهم
‭in Jesus Christ (Isaiah 63 14)
‮في يسوع المسيح ‮(إشعياء ٣٦ ٤١)
‭To know the Spirit
‮لمعرفة الروح
‭therefore is to stand in continuity
‮لذلك هو الوقوف في الاستمرارية
‭with the Saints of all ages.
‮مع القديسين من جميع الأعمار‮.
‭God has promised,
‮وعد الله ‮،
‭his Spirit already to Israel,
‮روحه بالفعل لإسرائيل ‮،
‭His chosen people.
‮شعبه المختار‮.
‭We know that in the Old Testament,
‮نحن نعلم أنه في العهد القديم ‮،
‭various individuals experience a comfort of that Spirit.
‮العديد من الأفراد يختبرون راحة ذلك الروح‮.
‭Think of David,
‮فكر في ديفيد ‮،
‭for example (Psalm 51)
‮على سبيل المثال ‮(مزمور ١٥)
‭But God promised
‮لكن الله وعد
‭a far richer and broader work of the Spirit
‮عمل الروح أغنى وأوسع
‭than we might possibly imagine.
‮مما قد نتخيله‮.
‭Isaiah foretold of a righteous king
‮انبأ اشعياء بملك بار
‭whose administration would be like,
‮إدارته ستكون مثل ‮،
‭rivers of waters in a dry place
‮أنهار المياه في مكان جاف
‭and the transformation of the barren wilderness
‮وتحول البرية القاحلة
‭into a world filled with the fruit of righteousness (Isaiah 32).
‮إلى عالم مليء بثمار البر ‮(إشعياء ٢٣)‮.
‭When the Spirit,
‮عندما الروح ‮،
‭When the Spirit
‮عندما الروح
‭is poured out upon us from on high.
‮يسكب علينا من العلاء‮.
‭And then he goes on to say in Isaiah 44,
‮ثم يذهب ليقول في إشعياء ٤٤ ‮،
‭that the Spirit would be poured out on Israel,
‮حتى ينسكب الروح على إسرائيل ‮،
‭like a river
‮مثل النهر
‭of water on dry ground,
‮من الماء على الأرض الجافة ‮،
‭irrigating faithless souls to produce a people
‮سقي النفوس الكافرة لإنتاج الناس
‭who say I am the Lord's.
‮من يقول اني للرب‮.
‭And so the Spirit
‮وكذلك الروح
‭is the answer of God's covenantal faithfulness
‮هو جواب أمانة الله في العهد
‭to the chronic problem
‮للمشكلة المزمنة
‭of Israel's covenant breaking.
‮من كسر عهد إسرائيل‮.
‭You find that also in
‮تجد ذلك أيضًا في
‭the Book of Joel
‮كتاب يوئيل
‭that the Lord would pour out his Spirit upon all his people
‮أن يسكب الرب روحه على كل شعبه
‭that whosoever would call on the name
‮أن من ينادي بالاسم
‭of the Lord would be saved
‮من الرب سيخلص
‭(Joel 2:28 to 32).
‮‮(يوئيل ٢:٨٢ إلى ٢٣)‮.
‭So to study the work of the Holy Spirit
‮لذا لدراسة عمل الروح القدس
‭is to study heavenly work,
‮هو دراسة العمل السماوي ‮،
‭saving work.
‮إنقاذ العمل‮.
‭And work that abides forever.
‮والعمل الذي يبقى إلى الأبد‮.
‭Now,
‮حاليا‮،
‭of course,
‮بالطبع‮،
‭in the New Testament age you know,
‮في عصر العهد الجديد كما تعلم ‮،
‭that when Jesus rose from the dead
‮أنه عندما قام يسوع من بين الأموات
‭and ascended into heaven,
‮وصعد إلى الجنة
‭He poured out His Spirit
‮سكب روحه
‭in much larger measures than
‮بمقاييس أكبر بكثير من
‭had previously been known
‮كان معروفا من قبل
‭(Acts 2 17,
‮‮(أعمال ٢ ٧١ ‮،
‭through 21 and 33 and 34)
‮من خلال ١٢ و ٣٣ و ٤٣)
‭And Peter after his sermon is interrupted by
‮وانقطع بطرس بعد خطبته
‭thousands of people who are under great conviction of sin.
‮الآلاف من الناس الذين تحت تبكيت عظيم على الخطيئة‮.
‭Under it
‮تحته
‭and they cried out men and Brethren.
‮فصرخوا رجالا واخوة‮.
‭What shall we do?
‮ماذا عسانا نفعل؟
‭Peter said to them,
‮قال لهم بطرس:
‭repent and be baptized everyone of you
‮توبوا وليعتمدوا جميعكم
‭in the name of Jesus Christ.
‮باسم يسوع المسيح‮.
‭And you shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
‮وتنال عطية الروح القدس‮.
‭For the promise is unto you
‮لان الوعد لكم
‭and to your children
‮ولأطفالك
‭and to all that are afar off.
‮ولكل ما هو بعيد‮.
‭Even as many as the Lord,
‮حتى كل من الرب ‮،
‭Our God shall call (Acts 2: 38 and 39).
‮سيدعو إلهنا ‮(أعمال الرسل ٢: ٨٣ و ٩٣)‮.
‭And so the rest
‮وهكذا الباقي
‭of the New Testament writings,
‮من كتابات العهد الجديد ‮،
‭particularly Paul's Epistles,
‮ولا سيما رسائل بولس ‮،
‭are just filled with the Holy Spirit.
‮فقط من الروح القدس‮.
‭He speaks often
‮يتحدث كثيرا
‭about being born
‮عن ولادتهم
‭of the Spirit such as Galatians,
‮من الروح مثل غلاطية ‮،
‭4: 29.
‮٤:٩٢‮.
‭And he's talking constantly
‮وهو يتحدث باستمرار
‭about different aspects
‮حول الجوانب المختلفة
‭of the Spirit's saving work.
‮لعمل خلاص الروح‮.
‭Like we just read a few
‮كما قرأنا فقط القليل
‭of them to you from from Romans 8.
‮منهم من رومية ٨‮.
‭So if we treasure Christ as our only mediator,
‮لذلك إذا كنا نعتز بالمسيح باعتباره الوسيط الوحيد لدينا ‮،
‭we will also treasure the Holy Spirit
‮سوف نعتز أيضًا بالروح القدس
‭as Christ's great gift,
‮كهدية المسيح العظيمة ‮،
‭which is inseparable from Him,
‮الذي لا ينفصل عنه ‮،
‭to sinners (John 4
‮للخطاة ‮(يوحنا ٤
‭and again John 7).
‮ومرة أخرى يوحنا ٧)‮.
‭Jonathan Edwards put it this way.
‮وضع جوناثان إدواردز الأمر بهذه الطريقة‮.
‭"The sum of the blessings Christ sought
‮"مجموع البركات التي طلبها المسيح
‭by what he did and suffered
‮بما فعله وعانى
‭in the work of redemption,
‮في عمل الفداء ‮،
‭was the Holy Spirit,
‮كان الروح القدس ‮،
‭the Holy Spirit in His indwelling,
‮الروح القدس في سكنه ‮،
‭His influences and fruits
‮تأثيراته وثماره
‭is the sum of all grace,
‮هو مجموع كل نعمة ‮،
‭holiness,
‮قداسة‮،
‭comfort and joy,
‮الراحة والفرح ‮،
‭or in one word
‮أو في كلمة واحدة
‭of all the spiritual good Christ purchased
‮من كل خير روحي اقتناها المسيح
‭for men in this world.
‮للرجال في هذا العالم‮.
‭And is also the sum of all perfection,
‮وهو أيضًا مجموع كل كمال ‮،
‭glory,
‮مجد‮،
‭and eternal joy,
‮والفرح الأبدي ‮،
‭that he purchased
‮الذي اشتراه
‭for them in another world."
‮لهم في عالم آخر "‮.
‭That's an amazing quote by Edwards.
‮هذا اقتباس رائع من إدواردز‮.
‭And it certainly shows us
‮وهذا يظهر لنا بالتأكيد
‭that many today are minimizing
‮التي يقوم الكثيرون بتقليلها اليوم
‭the role of the ministry
‮دور الوزارة
‭of the Holy Spirit as
‮من الروح القدس
‭integral with the entire
‮متكامل مع الكل
‭sum of blessings
‮مجموع النعم
‭that God's people receive in salvation.
‮التي ينالها شعب الله في الخلاص‮.
‭John Brown of Headington
‮جون براون من هيدينغتون
‭put it this way,
‮ضعها بهذه الطريقة‮،
‭"Did Christ purchase the Holy Spirit?
‮"هل اقتنى المسيح الروح القدس؟
‭Christ purchased the Spirit's gifts,
‮اشترى المسيح مواهب الروح ‮،
‭and influences in applying redemption,
‮وتأثيرات في تطبيق الفداء ‮،
‭but not his being,
‮ولكن ليس كيانه ‮،
‭which is independent."
‮وهو مستقل "‮.
‭So the work of the Spirit
‮هكذا عمل الروح
‭in many ways
‮بطرق عدة
‭is the fruit
‮هي الفاكهة
‭of Christ's death and resurrection.
‮عن موت المسيح وقيامته‮.
‭Now,
‮حاليا‮،
‭salvation in Christ
‮الخلاص في المسيح
‭is appreciated and enjoyed therefore
‮هو موضع تقدير والاستمتاع لذلك
‭only by knowing the Holy Spirit
‮فقط بمعرفة الروح القدس
‭and his saving work.
‮وعمله المنقذ‮.
‭And this is one of the
‮وهذه واحدة من
‭greatest doctrines of the Reformation,
‮أعظم مذاهب الإصلاح ‮،
‭developed so thoroughly and then even
‮تم تطويره بدقة ثم حتى
‭augmented by the Puritans.
‮عززها المتشددون‮.
‭What a treasure Reformed theology brings us
‮يا له من كنز يجلبه لنا علم اللاهوت المصلح
‭about the saving ministry of the Holy Spirit.
‮حول خدمة خلاص الروح القدس‮.
‭In fact,
‮في الواقع‮،
‭BB Warfield called John Calvin
‮دعا BB Warfield جون كالفين
‭The Theologian of the Holy Spirit.
‮لاهوتي الروح القدس‮.
‭And Warfield went on to claim
‮واستمر وارفيلد في المطالبة
‭the developed doctrine
‮العقيدة المتطورة
‭of the work of the Holy Spirit
‮من عمل الروح القدس
‭is an exclusively Reformation doctrine,
‮هي عقيدة الإصلاح حصريًا ‮،
‭and more particularly a Reformed doctrine,
‮وعلى وجه الخصوص العقيدة الإصلاحية ‮،
‭and still more particularly a Puritan doctrine.
‮ولا يزال على وجه الخصوص عقيدة بيوريتانية‮.
‭And so,
‮وهكذا‮،
‭study of the Spirit
‮دراسة الروح
‭through Reformed experiential soteriology,
‮من خلال علم الخلاص التجريبي المُصلح ‮،
‭- that is,
‮- هذا هو‮،
‭salvation that we experience
‮الخلاص الذي نختبره
‭by the work
‮من خلال العمل
‭of the Spirit in the soul -
‮للروح في الروح -
‭opens up a vast wealth of wisdom
‮يفتح ثروة هائلة من الحكمة
‭and joy to the believer.
‮والفرح للمؤمن‮.